<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The curate's queries, and, the maligant [sic] or courtier's answer thereto, according to their known principles of policy, their methods, and ends obtained thereby.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02553</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51617691</idno>
  <idno type="VID">175195</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240901144</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7618</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171660</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">51617691</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02553)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175195)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2719:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The curate's queries, and, the maligant [sic] or courtier's answer thereto, according to their known principles of policy, their methods, and ends obtained thereby.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Scotland? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A satirical critique of contemporary government policy in Scotland towards the Covenanters.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Suggested country of publication and date from internal evidence.</note>
                  <note>P. [12] blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Covenanters --  Persecution --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Church and state --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175195:1"/>
            <head>The Curate's Queries, AND, The Maligant or Courtier's Answer thereto, according to their known Principles of Policy, their Methods, and Ends obtained thereby.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Query 1.</hi> Why doth the King grant a new Indulgence, to a People not of our Prelatick Judgment?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quer. 2.</hi> Why doth the King, after the Appearance in the Field against his Supremacy, and our Prelacy, indemnify so many?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quer. 3.</hi> Why doth the King take off the Inter-communing from others?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quer. 4.</hi> Why doth he liberate those out of the <hi>Basse-</hi> Prison, some of whom are known to be Eye-sores?</p>
            </argument>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received yours, and considered your Mind, and have comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all in the above-said Queries, and in Answer I may say, Indeed it is not for want of Ignorance, that makes you fear and question the King so in his Love to you, and Care of the Churches; for di<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you rightly look back, and consider, how little o<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>er Proceedi<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> before and after <hi>Pentland</hi> did succeed, while w<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> on in a Ch<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:175195:2"/>Cruelty and Severity; and considering also the great Success of the Change of our Course the years after <hi>Pentland,</hi> conforming to that <hi>Machiavillian</hi> Principle, <hi>Divide &amp; impera,</hi> Divide and command; seeing our <hi>Prelacy,</hi> and their <hi>Erastian</hi> Government, serve to drive on our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs, and bring the Consciences and Bodies of People to the blind Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of our Wills: For while we came above-board, with plain-like dealing, we did but engage them further to Unity, both in their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Practice, by their Oneness in Suffering, to their alleaged Head and Lord, which hindred and withstood his Majesty from coming to the free exercise of his Supremacy granted to him by you. So we, most like Mariners, tack about again, according as the Wind blows, and see if we can make our Port another way; that when the Iron Yoke of your Prelacy came to be discovered, and became wearisom to them, we might see how to shift, alter, and change their Necks from it, to the more se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and pleasant Yoke of Supremacy, as being more plausible and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to them, by their Golden Change of Liberty, through our small spun Thread, and termillian coloured Indulgence, which hath more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily effectuated our Designs, according to the experiences of some of those Men's Services in the old and first Divisions, one and thirty years ago; while privately they favoured and carried on our Design for us, and brought us to their Armies, and Places of Trust; yea, by their defending their own Practices defend us: as by their deposing and suspending Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters that were most active against us, as Mr. <hi>Guthry,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thomson,</hi> Mr. <hi>Steedmand, Wishart, Hog,</hi> and others; yea, when <hi>Strathen</hi> could not, nor would bow to use their Designs, how did they excommunicate him, which broke his Spirit? Therefore we were most ungrateful, not to bring them into Places of Trust in Kirk and State, and also to Profit, when we are like to work more effectually by them, these being for this long time pretty fast advancing our way, to which we could not reduce them by our Violence and Policies; they can lay them aside by their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. Yet some of you know nothing but Plain-Sailing, but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ye not, <hi>Qui nescit dissimulare, nescit regnare?</hi> That is, He who knows not how to dissemble, knows not how to reign. And therefore how needful a matter is it to change the Nurse, if we can but quietly cause t<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>m drink still by one or other; such in our Principles of implicit Faith and Loyalty, to his Majesty's absolute Supremacy, tho not under the <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tion of Compliance with the Lordly Prelacy, which by its bloody
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175195:2"/>Face so much affrighted and start led them, from that blind and kindly Obedience, into our absolute Authority, which these nine or ten years most of them are brought into, by the Fear and painted Face of Liberty, until of late, that some old and wily, tho young and squeamish sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mached, through their Nurses Inadvertency, and our too much Severity, have gotten borrowed Sucks at some other Breasts, and tasted of their old and natural Fare; and, as the three Children in <hi>Daniel,</hi> they will not look upon our King's lordly and genteel Dishes, because coming through the hands of Supremacy, and a little corrected from the first purity and simplicity, by that fine specifick of Prudence, which is cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously done, to qualify and allay the hot Spirits of the young ones coming up, that they may be fit, and come out, standing before their Prince in all Loyalty and Obedience. Yet I say, tho we permit the Ministers, our Stewards to garnish all with fair and general Flourishes against Popery, the great Turk, and Antichrist, the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and some other ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Sins, I grant it; true, we grant them not to come <hi>Nathan</hi> like, and tell the King, <hi>Thou art the Man:</hi> Wherefore ye People, look upon them as Court-Parasites, not declaring the whole Counsel of God.</p>
            <p>Therefore for our conveniency, and to satisfy the most pliable Humor of them, we have artificially added more Pipes; since they scare at the former indulged Streams, they may drink at the latter: but still ye may see it is from the same Fountain and Head of Supremacy, all of one kind and quality; yea, considering Circumstances, Time, and Way, this new one may be more effectual, because in the mean while (if God prevent it not) of <hi>Bothwel</hi> Business, they being on the one hand stumbled and affrighted from the former indulged Streams, and now distressed, they had gone to the only Fountain that never run dry, had we not interposed by this fair Offer, which hath loosen'd much of the Bent of their Soul, and divert their Eye to hear our Favours, which hath made them lose the Water-Gage. And if ye consider these Favours given them, you will find we sail as closely to the Wind as we can, to hail them: For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. You see by the Proclamation, dated <hi>June</hi> 9. 1679. wherein we grant them this Indulgence to Hous-Meetings, we have thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stricted them from Field-Meetings, as Randevouzes of Rebellion, under the pain of Death to the Preacher, and Fining to the Hearer; since which time all of them observe it, and shut doors, and put away the People, except some chancy Minister that doth otherwise; which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175195:3"/>seems to me a great piece of Conformity, and homologating with Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, aad denying that which they owned upon the Peril of Life, as their Duty.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Ye see, that this is not general and universal throughout all the Nation, but on this side of <hi>Tay;</hi> and their tacit Consent is acceptance and compliance with us, and for the more peaceable enjoying the rest of the Land.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That we keep the Seat of our Government from being pestred with them, that the young ones coming forward may be brought up in our Faith. — And to the end that none whom we justly suspect, shall under colour of this our Favour continue to preach Rebellion, Schism, and Heresy, all are to give Bond into the Council, conform to the said Proclamation; by which ye, or any that are not blind, may see clearly, seeing we process against their former Practices as such, and all those who will not lay a Confederacy as they have done, whom we grant this Liberty, ye see how our Courts and Prisons are fill'd of them; ye also see, how we only allow one Preacher to a Parish, and are to admit no Expectants hereafter, that shall enter, or have entred by the Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Clergy; so we take care that this Favour shall fall and die with themselves. And by that determining, that the Prelatick Clergy shall have the Government in their own hands, and we have them not only homologating, and submitting to the Supremacy, but therein they accept the Indulgence according to the foresaid Proclamations, and King's Letters, they condemn all the Appearances of their Brethren and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, in such course as we call Rebellion; which is materially all we seek, tho not formally all that the Prelatick Clergy have granted us. And for my part, seeing we have them all as in so many Fetters and Chains, and can make their own Lands be their Jaylors and Serjeants, to bring them in so, as one is to execute our Laws against the other: So that we will have not much ado with our standing Forces, except to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press and swallow up the dissenting protesting handful by our violence, which cannot with the other be catched with our pretended Liberty. And all this ye shall see in the said Proclamation done by his Majesty, according to the Power reserved to him by the 5th Act of the 2d Session of the 2d Parliament, which expresseth full his Supremacy.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:175195:3"/>
            <p> And in Answer to your Query, Why do we not take off or suspend the Inter-communing and Denunciation from others? And it is most needful for our ends, the better to blind the Eyes of those that are inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communed, and next go out to help their Brethren at <hi>Hamiltoun,</hi> of purpose to make them the more inconcerned, till they see us spoil their Brethren time about. But next ye see the other Proclamation dated <hi>July</hi> 27. containing his Majesty's Indemnity, mentioning the just Resentments we have of the rebellious Courses taken by some, in poysoning the People with Principles inconsistent with true Piety, and all human Safety, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by weakning our Authority: So that we still declare our thoughts of former Practices, and what we require in the future. And tho we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnify some of them, Ministers and Heritors are still excepted; and it is still upon conditions, that any who gets the Benefit of our Favour shall subscribe the Bond, not to lift up Arms, do what we will. So that ye see what we get not of their Purses, vve get of their Consciences. And to speak the plain truth of it, it was more to indemnify our dead, least the Chase may turn, and to put a dash on Duke <hi>Hamiltoun</hi>'s Party, than any real Favours to others.</p>
            <p>But ye may ask, why we indemnify all such as have spoken, printed, written, or published any traiterous Speeches, or infamous Libels, or Pasquils? I say, ye may hereafter see, and have already seen the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency therefore, since our pressing the Bond, and keeping the Circuit-Courts, and so forth: for dexterous Robbers, when they mind to assault a House, will study to make a Friend first within, or see to cast a Bone in the Dog's mouth, that he may not bark; and you see, how some of them by preaching, others by writing Letters, and the <hi>Scots</hi> Grievances, that they awakened and allarm'd the Country thereby, especially at the time of the <hi>High land</hi> Host being in the West, when we press'd that Bond; but now by this Bond of Favour, how do those lie very quietly, and very ordinarily ye may know one or two barking, who used formerly to cry loudest and longest, will cause the Hue and Cry so much more their si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and favouring and conjoining with you, will make all the rest fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and become silent, when they see those who used to cry loudest, to become most silent: so that we gain forty for one to take the Bond, and pay the Sesse for the very Letters of Advice to that end, which all our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175195:4"/>Force and Policy could not have done. But would ever the People after Bishop <hi>Sharp's</hi> death, have compeared, and purged themselves, so ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally as they did, if Mr. — had not written a zealous Letter for that end, which was often read, but no Copies given after the end was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. But can any single the Sheep so well as the Shepherd? because they are not afraid of them, and least looking for it from him who should feed and defend them, and so by them they are the easier taken in the Snare, and sold to the Butchers for the Shambles. Can any deliver up the City so easily as the Keeper? Can any storm a Fort, or surprize a Party so ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily, as when the Watch is off the Wall; tho fled to the Camp, or though upon the Wall, if either they be asleep, or silent by consent? Or can we pacify the Multitude, till we blind the Ringleaders, whereby it is now seen Bribes blind Eyes, and bribes the mouth of the Wise, and may be understood in any thing, whether Money, Gifts, or Favours, by which ye can work upon, prevail, or gain your Point. Great Men are not always wise, nor wise Men always honest, so consequentially they are not always; for the true Wisdom of the wise is not always proved by their Wit, but by their Ways; so also Fools in the World's eyes, their Wisdom is seen in choice, not in their ways.</p>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The second Part of the Fruits and Effects of Indulgence.</head>
               <p>We see that former Indulgences have so conformed the Gentry, and for the most part of the Nobles, that they are all our kind Fouls, not only to be Hearers of the indulged, but the most part of them, and even the pretended strictest, and most close Walkers in Judgment, in reference to all the Articles of Truth, attended our Army when we fought the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, with their Swords drawn, riding in Battel with the rest, incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating themselves with us, and have done ever since, in offering to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press Preaching every where; yea, would be willing to be at the labour to do more violence than we, if we would allow Wages proportionable; but yet did more generally compear at our Circuit-Courts, and did wait, attend, convoy again the Lords of the Circuit, which is virtually an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving our ways, our selves, our Courts, and condemning our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; and ye fee how few Gentlemen of Quality did adjoin with, or approve those in Arms at <hi>Bothwell,</hi> but generally cried out, censured, and condemned, being taught more peaceable Principles than that of defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175195:4"/>Arms, since our former Indulgences. So that we must not be too strict, whether they go up to worship to <hi>Dan</hi> your Prelacy, or <hi>Bethel</hi> your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence; for it is still the Golden Calf of Supremacy that is bowed to, or acknowledged, or worshipped in either of them. We must take all fair, that they go up to <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and keep down the publick Meetings in the Field, wherein they have spoken so much of their Covenants, and former Works of Reformation, whereby they subdue the Hearts of the People from the King's Supremacy, that Idol of Jealousy, whereto they, <hi>Mordecai</hi> like, will not bow to our <hi>Haman,</hi> since which time they are the Party most terrible to us. And therefore it is not best for us, since we have divided them, and most part of them gaping and inclining after Peace, Ease and Rest, to take the opportunity to gratify them thus, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially considering it begets a near and better Union and Harmony with us? For tho our first work was to divide them one from another, our next work is, to grant Liberty and Peace, till we make them one with our selves.</p>
               <p>And have we not succeeded, when we have planted them where we pleased, and have transported again, they having received our Counsel and Commands, answering at our Courts are silenced, deposed, shorte<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or longer, while as we please, giving or not giving the Commission, as we please, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>John Sinkla<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> of <hi>Ormistone;</hi> After Preparation-Sermon, Sermon and all was stopt, except to eat the Pread, and drink the Wine at home, and sow or none at all indulged, or not indulged, that spake against the paying of the Sesse, or taking our Bonds; but on the contrary, advises to, and protests for the same: and now our old Friends, Indulgence with them, are not only so cordial and joint together, but by their wise carriage they cunningly manage Affairs to such advantage, both in their private Meetings, where they first begin and prepare things, but also in their general Assemblies, where they next pump and spy out the Inclinations of the rest; and if they cannot being things to their desirable conclusions, they cry out with one voice, Let us study Union, and shun all Debates tending to Division; by which they frighten some, or blass others into a silence, or full compliance with themselves, because the poor Men love so much their own ease, and partly lest they should <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd them for Dividers. So that we see the great advantage in placing the indulged
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175195:5"/>where we pleased, mixed the Resolutioners with the Protesters, especially casting two or three leading Men of the Resolutioners in every Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, to incline the rest to all quiet and peaceable things. What need we bring Mr. <hi>Hutchison</hi> out of the East, and Mr. <hi>Alexander Watherbourne</hi> out of the North, to <hi>Irving</hi> Presbytery; and Mr. <hi>John Bairdie,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Will. Eccles,</hi> to <hi>Paslay</hi> Presbytery; and Mr. <hi>Violat</hi> to <hi>Cledsdale,</hi> and others: for they had idle Ministers a number of their own, who preached not in the Fields. But so it is, by this mixing, they being generally pitch'd upon as Moderators or leading Members, they have not only reformed these Presbyteries, but have prepared things to our hand, as it is at this very day; for tho many of them did not accept of the first Indulgence, nor would go, nor dwell in, nor be confined to the indulged Prisons, yet for the most part they have still confined themselves to <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> which has gained the most part of our Design, which was from keeping of them from preaching unto the Country: But at <hi>Edenburgh</hi> they preach none, or but to two or three Ladies, that know little what others suffer, and whom, tho they will not hear the Curats, yet for fear of losing their Estates they will not go to Field-meetings: Fear of their good Name hinders them in one, and Estates in another; all which hath habituated them to more Ease, and a new Indulgence, especially through the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the professing Ladies, who have so influenced them to a lassy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementing laxe, partial way in the Matters of God, preaching rather to the Humors of the Hearers, than home to their Consciences; and many a time by the Ladies, we plow with their Heifers; for it is not as it was in the old time, when the old Laird was with the Court, and the young with the Kirk; but now both old and young are against this dissenting, protesting Party, except a few of the meanest; and all the Ladies for most part, tho dissenting from your Prelacy, yet are very fond upon this new Indulgence, and they cry out a Confederacy with them, otherwise they must be branded. And it is to be feared, that Ladies and others are more to be consulted than ruling Elders, or the suffering Party; and that not only because of their consent in things, but considering their Purses are able to manage and carry on the Lord's Matters at Court, by Money and Policy; as by the first and last Embassies sent out by us, dividing the rest, and by the Heritors or Lairds bonding for the Ministers, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be gotten done by these, all of a strict Presbyterian Principle. So that we reconcile the Malignants and them, and get them to be their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175195:5"/>Favourites, if not often made ruling and leading Elders, which in time works and begets a Familiarity, Singleness, Oneness, tho not in all things; and hereby we shall bring them nearer to us, but not we to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> But you say, <hi>Why do we liberate those out of the</hi> Bass?</p>
               <p>I assure you, our freeing of these was a very wise act; for, first, the People, and many others, both Ministers and Gentry, would never have believed us, nor hearkned to any thing of our Favours, if we had kept them in.</p>
               <p>Next, their Tongues and Pens would have been more resiless in it, than now when they are out of it, and done us much more hurt by their writing and testifying against the rest: Whereas now most of them three mainly excepted, whom I ever feared, are the best Coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducks could have been gotten ever since, to draw in many of the wild Mountaineers, especially since we have a silver Chain at their feet, to draw them where we please, as to a Prison. And as for my part, the blacking Paper to us, and not against us, all Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances considered, is a great Conformity, at least, a great Help for forwarding our Designs; for our yeelding to them, of letting them out of Prison, is not a yeelding to the Cause whereupon they were liberate; for, as cunning Fishers, we let one Bait go with them, that we may the better dispose them for the next, where the Hook is carefully hid; and indeed we are like to do it, and I pray keep quiet, gumble not the Water, speak not a word, for they swim about, and most of them are picking kindly, and several of them are hooked already. When there were seventy Ministers at the Assembly, there were sixty one that voted for accepting the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgencee, and giving Bond, and only eight or nine that were <hi>Non-liquents.</hi> But there is a very few who are like to scent us out, for they will not so much as believe our sweet Musick, let be Dance at our Piping; I wish they may not scare the rest, because of their absenting. It is true, some of the seventy, who first voted for Heretors giving Bond, began to grumble, when they did see the nature of the Bond; but did they expect, that tho we should guild ir anew, and that we will still have it carry and imply the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175195:6"/>Tincture of our Sin, <hi>quod est,</hi> Supremacy, for promoting our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs, else why grant we it? But may we not think our Favours well bestowed upon the old, when it works so with the young, tho ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted from the benefit of the same, either at present or for ever, if we can help it? It must be strong Liqnor, that not only intoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates them who drink it, but those who suck their Breasts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; for whereas I expected, that the young should have dissented and protested for their Interest, yet how kind are they all for one T<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Union, Peace, and that upon any terms. Yea, ye could scarce wish more of them; for ye shall hear twenty words for Union and Peace for one word for the Truth, or for these persecuted for the Truth, and with a general dislike of Zeal, as if blind Zeal, except it be dash, and so well purled with Prudence, as it may please the Palates of all those who hear of it. While Bishop <hi>Lightonne</hi> and others drive this Design for us, in pleading for Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Sobriety, from Love and Sobriety, how bitterly do they bark at them, and for all their Papers and Defences, how did they therein scorn them, <hi>Gallio</hi> like, as if both they and the indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Brethren were Proof from not only their Threatning, but also their Favours and Flatteries; yea, they will not dance to their piping, yet to the same Spring, when the Instrument is in other hands: for now how are they who wrote? The Answer to the Dialogues, <hi>Samson</hi> like, does more execution for us than a thousand; so that I was ever of that opinion, that a wedge of their own Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber would split them best; for Dirt cast on by those hands, sticks greatly better than by our hands, upon the hunted Brethren's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and puts them to a Non-plus and Consternation, except those well fixed, they are soon overshadowed and broken down, by the Fall of such tall Cedars. Wherefore you see our Work is made easy, for when we empty their Purses, and by our quarterings and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, have them as so many Buckets, one going down, its weight helps up another. And ye may know, when we have impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished and divided a People, it is the easier suppressing and ruling them as we will, and they less able to resist; yea, how did we make the Citizens guard their Ministers and Brethren to the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, and not only be Witnesses, but Executioners of our Decrees? And are they not contented, poor Souls, to keep their Privileges of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175195:6"/>their own Guard, than the greatest of Privileges, by which it seem God has left them to do our Drudgeries? For how did the most part of their Professors, as well as others, muster, and wait for our Orders, watching the Council and City of <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and so have them sworn to our Colours, until we by our other Forces subdued the Rebels; yea, helped us to watch, guard, attend the Prisoners, and to set up the Trophies of Victory with their Robes at the Cross one hour, and the next hour guarding some to seal with their Blood against them. And how are they all generally, over all places that we come, at once enchanted with our Favours, hanging about our hands, courting us, flattering us, and our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, touching the meanest People to such familiarity and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance, as things less fundamental, remote, and not so essential to Salvation. So to conclude, we are now one, and there is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence amongst us.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>